My son and the iPhone were born three weeks apart
كان الفرق بين ولادة ابني و الـ iPhone ثلاث أسابيع
in June 2007.
في يونيو 2007
So while those early adopters were lined up outside,
بينما كان المستهلكون المبكرون يصطفون خارج متاجر آبل
waiting to get their hands on this amazing new gadget,
منتظرين الحصول على هذه الأجهزة الجديدة والمذهلة
I was stuck at home with my hands full of something else
كنت عالقة في البيت ويداي مشغولتان بشيء آخر
that was sending out constant notifications --
يرسل تنبيهات مستمرة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
a miserable, colicky baby
طفل ممغوص،
who would only sleep in a moving stroller with complete silence.
لا ينام إلا في عربة متحركة وفي هدوءٍ تام.
I literally was walking 10 to 15 miles a day,
وكنت أمشي من 10 إلى 15 ميل في اليوم
and the baby weight came off.
كان وزني بعد الولادة يتناقص
That part was great.
كان ذلك شيئًا عظيمًا.
But man, was I bored.
لكن كنت أشعر بالملل.
Before motherhood, I had been a journalist
قبل الأمومة كنت تلك الصحفية
who rushed off when the Concorde crashed.
التي هرعت لتغطية خبر تحطم طائرة الكونكورد.
I was one of the first people into Belgrade
كنت من أوائل الناس الذين دخلوا بلجراد
when there was a revolution in Serbia.
حينما حدثت الثورة في صربيا.
Now, I was exhausted.
أما الآن، فأنا منهكة.
This walking went on for weeks.
استمر ذلك المشي لأسابيع.
It was only until about three months in that something shifted, though.
إلا أن الوضع لم يتغير إلا بعد ثلاثة أشهر.
As I pounded the pavement,
بينما كنت أبحث عن عمل،
my mind started to wander, too.
بدأ عقلي في التفكير أيضًا.
I began imagining what I would do when I finally did sleep again.
بدأت أتخيل ماذا يمكنني أن أفعل حينما أستطيع العودة للنوم مرة أخرى.
So the colic did fade,
إذن تلاشى الغص اخيراً،
and I finally got an iPhone
و أخيرًا حصلت على جهاز iPhone
and I put all those hours of wandering into action.
واستطعت أن أحول ساعات التفكير إلى عمل على أرض الواقع
I created my dream job hosting a public radio show.
نفذت العمل الذي كنت أحلم به وهو استضافة برنامج إذاعي
So there was no more rushing off to war zones,
ولم يعد هناك اندفاع إلى ساحات الحروب
but thanks to my new smartphone,
والشكر لجهازي الذكي الجديد،
I could be a mother and a journalist.
بإمكاني أن أكون صحفية وأمًا في ذات الوقت.
I could be on the playground and on Twitter at the same time.
بإمكاني أن أكون في ساحة الألعاب وعلى توتير في ذات الوقت.
Yeah, well, when I thought that,
نعم، كان هذا ما فكرت فيه،
when the technology came in and took over,
حينما جاءت التكنولوجيا وتولّت الأمر،
that is when I hit a wall.
حينها لم أستطع ان أتقدم في عملي.
So, I want you to picture this:
أريد أن تتصورو هذا:
you host a podcast, and you have to prove
أنك تستضيف بودكاست، ولا بد أن تثبت
that the investment of precious public radio dollars in you
أنك تستحق استثمار دولارات الشبكة الإذاعية
is worth it.
في برنامجك.
My goal was to increase my audience size tenfold.
كان هدفي هو زيادة عدد المستمعين عشرات الأضعاف
So one day, I sat down to brainstorm,
وفي يوم ما، أقمت جلسة عصف ذهني
as you do,
كما يفعل أي شخص،
and I came up barren.
إلا أنها كانت غير مثمرة.
This was different than writer's block, right?
كان الأمر يختلف عن حالة قفلة الكاتب.
It wasn't like there was something there waiting to be unearthed.
لم يكن الأمر كأن هناك فكرة ستخرج من الأعماق.
There was just nothing.
بل لم يكن هناك شيء.
And so I started to think back:
بدأت في إعادة التفكير:
When was the last time I actually had a good idea?
متى كانت آخر مرة خطرت لي فكرة جيدة؟
Yeah, it was when I was pushing that damn stroller.
نعم، حينما كنت أدفع بتلك العربة.
Now all the cracks in my day were filled with phone time.
أما الآن فكل أوقات الفراغ في اليوم تذهب في الانشغال بالهاتف
I checked the headlines while I waited for my latte.
أتصفح العناوين خلال انتظاري للقهوة.
I updated my calendar while I was sitting on the couch.
أحدّث جدولي خلال جلوسي على الأريكة في الصالة
Texting turned every spare moment
أو أنشغل بإرسال رسائل نصية في كل لحظة فراغ
into a chance to show to my coworkers and my dear husband
لأثبت لزملائي في العمل ولزوجي العزيز
what a responsive person I was,
أني شخص متجاوب،
or at least it was a chance to find another perfect couch
أو على الأقل أبحث عن أريكة جميلة أخرى لأصورها وأضعها
for my page on Pinterest.
على صفحتي في Pinterest
I realized that I was never bored.
ولاحظت أني لم أشعر بالملل إطلاقاً.
And anyway, don't only boring people get bored?
وفي كل الأحوال، أليس الأشخاص المملين هم من يشعروا بالملل؟
But then I started to wonder:
لكني بدأت اتسائل:
What actually happens to us when we get bored?
ماذا يحدث حقًا حينما نشعر بالملل؟
Or, more importantly: What happens to us if we never get bored?
أو الأكثر الأهمية: ماذا يحصل لنا حينما لا نشعر بالملل إطلاقًا؟
And what could happen if we got rid of this human emotion entirely?
وماذا يمكن أن يحدث حينما نتخلص من هذا الشعور الإنساني تمامًا؟
I started talking to neuroscientists and cognitive psychologists,
بدأت بالتحدث إلى علماء الأعصاب وعلماء النفس المعرفي،
and what they told me was fascinating.
وكان ما قالوه لي مذهلًا.
It turns out that when you get bored,
اتضح أنه حينما تشعر بالملل،
you ignite a network in your brain called the "default mode."
فإنك تشعل شبكة أعصاب في دماغك تُسمى "الوضع الافتراضي"
So our body, it goes on autopilot while we're folding the laundry
إذن فأجسادنا تكون على الوضع الآلي ونحن نطوي الملابس
or we're walking to work,
أو ونحن نمشي للعمل،
but actually that is when our brain gets really busy.
لكن في الواقع أنه في هذه الأوقات يكون الدماغ مشغولًا جدًا.
Here's boredom researcher Dr. Sandi Mann.
هنا الباحثة في شعور الملل، الدكتورة ساندي مان.
(Audio) Dr. Sandi Mann: Once you start daydreaming
(صوت) د.ساندي مان: حينما تبدأ في أحلام اليقظة
and allow your mind to really wander,
وتسمح لعقلك للتفكّر،
you start thinking a little bit beyond the conscious,
فأنت تبدأ بالتفكير وراء الوعي قليلًا
a little bit into the subconscious,
نوعًا ما في اللاوعي،
which allows sort of different connections to take place.
الأمر الذي يسمح بحدوث نوع مختلف من الارتباطات.
It's really awesome, actually.
إنه حقًا مذهل في الحقيقة
Manoush Zomorodi: Totally awesome, right?
إنه مذهل تمامًا، أليس كذلك؟
So this is my brain in an fMRI,
هذا دماغي في أشعة الرنين المغناطيسي،
and I learned that in the default mode is when we connect disparate ideas,
وقد تعلمت أننا في الوضع الافتراضي نربط بين الأفكار المختلفة
we solve some of our most nagging problems,
نحل أصعب مشكلاتنا
and we do something called "autobiographical planning."
ونقوم بعمل أمر يسمّى "تخطيط السيرة الذاتية"
This is when we look back at our lives,
ويحدث حينما ننظر للخلف في حياتنا،
we take note of the big moments, we create a personal narrative,
ونحتفظ بأهم اللحظات، وننشئ قصة شخصية
and then we set goals
ومن ثم نضع أهداف
and we figure out what steps we need to take to reach them.
ونحدد الخطوات التي نحتاجها للوصول لتلك الأهداف.
But now we chill out on the couch also while updating a Google Doc
لكن الحال الآن هو أننا نجلس ببرود على الأريكة ونحدث مستند ما على جوجل
or replying to email.
أو نقوم بالرد على إيميل ما.
We call it "getting shit done,"
نسمي هذا "الانتهاء من الأعمال المقرفة"
but here's what neuroscientist Dr. Daniel Levitin says
لكن هنا ما يقوله عالم الأعصاب الدكتور دانيل ليفتن
we're actually doing.
عمّا نفعله حقًّا.
(Audio) Dr. Daniel Levitin: Every time you shift your attention
(صوت) د.دانيل ليفتن: في كل مرة تقوم بتحويل انتباهك
from one thing to another,
من أمر لآخر،
the brain has to engage a neurochemical switch
يشارك الدماع بعملية تبديل كيميائية عصبية
that uses up nutrients in the brain to accomplish that.
التي تستخدم مواد مغذية في الدماغ لتحقيق ذلك.
So if you're attempting to multitask,
إذن فحينما تحاول القيام بأكثر من مهمة في ذات الوقت
you know, doing four or five things at once,
ربما أربع أو خمس أمور في ذات الوقت،
you're not actually doing four or five things at once,
فأنت في الحقيقة لا تقوم بأربع أو خمس أمور في آن واحد
because the brain doesn't work that way.
لأن الدماغ لا يعمل بهذه الطريقة.
Instead, you're rapidly shifting from one thing to the next,
في المقابل، أنت تتنقل سريعًا من أمر لآخر
depleting neural resources as you go.
وتستنفد الموارد العصبية أثناء ذلك
(Audio) MZ: So switch, switch, switch, you're using glucose, glucose, glucose.
(صوت مانوش): إذن تغيير يتبعه تغيير يتبعه تغيير وتستخدم المزيد من الجلوكوز
(Audio) DL: Exactly right, and we have a limited supply of that stuff.
(صوت): تمامًا، ونحن لدينا كمية محدودة من هذه المواد.
MZ: A decade ago, we shifted our attention at work
(مانوش) قبل عقد من الزمن كنا نغير انتباهنا في العمل
every three minutes.
كل ثلاث دقائق.
Now we do it every 45 seconds,
أما الآن فكل 45 ثانية
and we do it all day long.
بل ونفعل ذلك طوال اليوم.
The average person checks email 74 times a day,
معدل اطلاع الإنسان على إيميله هو 74 مرة في اليوم
and switches tasks on their computer
ويتنقّل في مهامه على الكمبيوتر
566 times a day.
566 مرة في اليوم.
I discovered all this talking to professor of informatics,
اكتشفت كل هذه المعلومات عبر الحديث مع أستاذ علم المعلومات
Dr. Gloria Mark.
الدكتور جلوريا مارك.
(Audio) Dr. Gloria Mark: So we find that when people are stressed,
(صوت) د.جلوريا: إذن فقد وجدنا أنه حين يكون الناس تحت بعض الضغوط
they tend to shift their attention more rapidly.
فإنهم يحولون انتباههم من أمر لآخر سريعًا
We also found, strangely enough,
ووجدنا أيضًا وبشكل غريب،
that the shorter the amount of sleep that a person gets,
أن نوم الشخص لساعات قليلة
the more likely they are to check Facebook.
يصاحبه ازدياد الساعات التي يقضيها على فيس بوك
So we're in this vicious, habitual cycle.
إذن فنحن ندور في دائرة عادات مفرغة.
MZ: But could this cycle be broken?
(مانوش): لكن هل من الممكن كسر هذه الدائرة؟
What would happen if we broke this vicious cycle?
ماذا قد يحدث إذا كسرنا هذه الدائرة الشريرة؟
Maybe my listeners could help me find out.
ربما يستطيع المستمعون مساعدتي في ذلك.
What if we reclaimed those cracks in our day?
ماذا لو أصلحنا هذه الشقوق في يومنا؟
Could it help us jump-start our creativity?
هل من الممكن أن تساعدنا لنبدأ إبداعاتنا؟
We called the project "Bored and Brilliant."
أطلقنا على المشروع اسم "ضجر ومميز."
And I expected, you know, a couple hundred people to play along,
وتوقعت أن ينضم للمشروع بضع مئات فقط
but thousands of people started signing up.
لكن سجل الآلاف ضمن المشروع.
And they told me the reason they were doing it
وكان السبب الذي جعلهم يشاركون كما حدثوني
was because they were worried that their relationship with their phone
أنهم قلقون من علاقتهم بهواتفهم
had grown kind of ... "codependent," shall we say.
ومن الممكن أنه أصبح لديهم نوع من ... " التعلق العاطفي " كما يُقال.
(Audio) Man: The relationship between a baby and its teddy bear
(صوت رجل): العلاقة التي بين طفل ودميته الدب
or a baby and its binky
أو بين طفلة ودميتها العروسة
or a baby that wants its mother's cradle
أو طفل يريد أن يكون في حضن والدته
when it's done with being held by a stranger --
حينما يكون محتجزًا بين يدي شخص غريب
(Laughs)
(ضحك)
that's the relationship between me and my phone.
هذه هي العلاقة بيني وبين هاتفي.
(Audio) Woman: I think of my phone like a power tool:
(صوت امرأة): أفكر في هاتفي كأنه أداة قوة لي
extremely useful, but dangerous if I'm not handling it properly.
مفيد للغاية، لكنه خَطِر إذا لم استعمله بشكل صحيح.
(Audio) Woman 2: If I don't pay close attention,
(صوت امرأة): إذا لم أُعطي انتباهي للوقت
I'll suddenly realize that I've lost an hour of time
فسأتفاجئ بأني أمضيت ساعة من وقتي
doing something totally mindless.
في أمور لا أهمية لها.
MZ: OK, but to really measure any improvement,
(مانوش): حسنًا، لقياس أي تقدم
we needed data, right?
فنحن نحتاج إلى بيانات صحيح؟
Because that's what we do these days.
هكذا نفعل هذه الأيام.
So we partnered with some apps that would measure how much time
إذن عقدنا شراكة مع تطبيقات أخرى تقيس كمية الوقت
we were spending every day on our phone.
الذي نقضيه كل يوم ونحن نمسك بهواتفنا.
If you're thinking it's ironic
إذا ظننتم أن الأمر سخرية
that I asked people to download another app
لأننا نطلب من الناس أن يحمّلوا تطبيقًا آخر
so that they would spend less time on their phones:
ليقللوا من مدة جلوسهم على هواتفهم:
yeah, but you gotta meet people where they are.
فنعم إنه كذلك، لكن لا بد أن تستمعوا لهؤلاء الناس
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So before challenge week,
إذن فقبل أسبوع التحدي،
we were averaging two hours a day on our phones
كنا نستخدم هواتفنا بمعدل ساعتين يوميًا
and 60 pickups,
ونلتقطه 60 مرة،
you know, like, a quick check, did I get a new email?
نزعم أننا نريد معرفة إذا كان هناك رسالة جديدة مثلاً
Here's what Tina, a student at Bard College,
هنا تخبرنا تينا الطالبة في كلية Bard
discovered about herself.
بما اكتشفته عن نفسها
(Audio) Tina: So far, I've been spending
(صوت تينا): كنت استخدم الهاتف
between 150 and 200 minutes on my phone per day,
لمدة تتراوح بين 150 إلى 200 دقيقة في اليوم
and I've been picking up my phone 70 to 100 times per day.
وكنت التقطته من 70 إلى 100 مرة يوميًا
And it's really concerning,
كان أمرًا جديرًا بالانتباه
because that's so much time that I could have spent
لأنه كان بإمكاني قضاء هذا الوقت
doing something more productive, more creative, more towards myself,
في فعل أمر آخر أكثر انتاجية وإبداعًا،
because when I'm on my phone, I'm not doing anything important.
لأنني كنت استخدم الهاتف في أمور لا أهمية لها
MZ: Like Tina, people were starting to observe their own behavior.
(مانوش): بدأ الناس في مراقبة سلوكهم مثل تينا
They were getting ready for challenge week.
وبدأوا بالاستعداد لأسبوع التحدي،
And that Monday,
وفي يوم الإثنين،
they started to wake up to instructions in their inbox,
استيقظوا على التعليمات التي وصلتهم في بريدهم الإلكتروني،
an experiment to try.
بدأت التجربة
Day one:
اليوم الأول:
"Put it in your pocket."
"ضعه في جيبك"
Take that phone out of your hand.
ضع هاتفك بعيدًا عن متناول يديك.
See if you can eliminate the reflex to check it all day long,
وانظر إذا كنت تستطيع مقاومة الشعور اللإرادي بمعرفة الجديد
just for a day.
فقط ليوم واحد.
And if this sounds easy,
إذا كنتم ترونه أمرًا بسيطًا
you haven't tried it.
فأنتم لم تجربوه بعد.
Here's listener Amanda Itzko.
أماندا اتزكو تحدثنا.
(Audio) Amanda Itzko: I am absolutely itching.
(صوت أماندا): أنا جدًا متلهّفة لمعرفة الجديد.
I feel a little bit crazy,
أشعر أنني مجنونة نوعًا ما
because I have noticed that I pick up my phone
لأنني لاحظت أنني التقطت هاتفي
when I'm just walking from one room to another,
وأنا أسير من غرفة لأخرى،
getting on the elevator,
وأنا في المصعد،
and even -- and this is the part that I am really embarrassed
حتى - وهذا أمرٌ محرجٌ للغاية
to actually say out loud --
أنا أقول ذلك في العلن -
in the car.
وأنا في السيارة.
MZ: Yikes.
مانوش: نعم
Yeah, well, but as Amanda learned,
حسنٌ لكن أماندا تعلمت
this itching feeling is not actually her fault.
أن هذا الشعور باللهفة ليس خطأها.
That is exactly the behavior that the technology is built to trigger.
إنه تمامًا السلوك الذي صُنعت التقنية لتحرّكه في دواخلنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, right?
أليس ذلك صحيحًا؟
Here's former Google designer, Tristan Harris.
هنا يحدثنا مصمم جوجل السابق، تريستان هاريس.
(Audio) Tristan Harris: If I'm Facebook or I'm Netflix or I'm Snapchat,
(صوت تريسان): في أي تطبيق تستخدمه فيسبوك أو نتفليكس أو سناب شات
I have literally a thousand engineers
فهناك - حرفيًّا - آلاف المهندسين
whose job is to get more attention from you.
عملهم هو جذب انتباهك أكثر
I'm very good at this,
أنا جيّد جدًا في هذا،
and I don't want you to ever stop.
ولا أريدك أن تقف أبدًا.
And you know, the CEO of Netflix recently said,
هل تعرفون لقد قال مدير نتفليكس التنفيذي
"Our biggest competitors are Facebook, YouTube and sleep."
"أن أكبر منافسينا هم فيسبوك، واليوتيوب، والنوم"
I mean, so there's a million places to spend your attention,
هناك ملايين الأماكن التي قد تجذب الانتباه
but there's a war going on to get it.
ولكن خلفها حرب مستمرة للحصول على انتباهك
MZ: I mean, you know the feeling:
(مانوش): ربما تعرفون ذلك الشعور
that amazing episode of "Transparent" ends,
في نهاية حلقة رائعة من مسلسل "Transparent"
and then the next one starts playing
ثم تبدأ الحلقة التي تليها مباشرة
so you're like, eh, OK fine, I'll just stay up and watch it.
وأنتم تقولون " أوه، لا بأس، سأشاهد هذه الحلقة فقط "
Or the LinkedIn progress bar says you are this close
أو عندما يُظهر لكم LinkedIn أنكم قريبون جدًا
to having the perfect profile,
من جعل صفحتكم مثالية ومتقنة
so you add a little more personal information.
فتضيف المزيد من المعلومات.
As one UX designer told me,
قال لي أحد مصممي الـ UX (تجربة المستخدم)
the only people who refer to their customers as "users"
أن الوحيدون الذين يطلقون اسم "مستخدمين" على عملائهم
are drug dealers and technologists.
هم بائعي المخدرات والتقنيون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And users, as we know, are worth a lot of money.
وكما قد تعلمون، فالمستخدمون يساوون الكثير من المال
Here's former Facebook product manager and author,
هنا يحدثنا الؤلف ومدير الإنتاج في فيس بوك
Antonio García Martínez.
أنطونيو جارسيا مارتينيز
(Audio) Antonio García Martínez: The saying is, if any product is free
(صوت أنطونيو): العبارة المعروفة تقول، إذا كانت المنتج مجاني
then you're the product; your attention is the product.
فاعلم أنك أنت المنتج، إذن انتباهك هو المنتج المطلوب.
But what is your attention worth?
لكن بماذا يقدر انتباهك؟
That's why literally every time you load a page,
لهذا السبب فإنه في كل مرة تحمّل صفحة ما
not just on Facebook or any app,
ليس فقط الفيسبوك بل أي تطبيق آخر
there's an auction being held instantly, billions of times a day,
فإن مزادًا يبدأ مباشرة، مليارات المرات يوميًا،
for exactly how much that one ad impression cost.
لمعرفة قيمة تكلفة ظهور الإعلان الواحد.
MZ: By the way, the average person will spend two years of their life
(مانوش): بالمناسبة، فإن الشخص العادي ينفق سنتين من عمره
on Facebook.
في تصفح الفيس بوك.
So, back to challenge week.
عودة لأسبوع التحدي.
Immediately, we saw some creativity kick in.
فقد رأينا مباشرة انطلاق بعض الإبداع.
Here's New Yorker Lisa Alpert.
هنا ليزا ألبرت من نيويورك.
(Audio) Lisa Alpert: I was bored, I guess.
(صوت ليزا): كنت أشعر بالملل.
So I suddenly looked at the stairway that went up to the top of the station,
ونظرت فجأة في الدرج الموصل لأعلى المحطة
and I thought, you know,
وفكرت،
I had just come down that stairway, but I could go back up
أنني للتو ذهبت للأسفل عبر هذا الدرج وباستطاعتي العودة لأعلى مجددًا
and then come back down and get a little cardio.
ثم النزول لأسفل وبهذا أكون مارست بعض الرياضة
So I did,
وفعلت.
and then I had a little more time, so I did it again and I did it again,
ثم كان لدي مزيد من الوقت، ففعلت ذلك مجددًا،
and I did it 10 times.
ثم فعلت ذلك 10 مرات.
And I had a complete cardio workout.
وهكذا انتهيت من حصة رياضة كاملة
I got on that R train feeling kind of exhausted,
صعدت القطار وأنا أشعر بالتعب
but, like, wow, that had never occurred to me.
لكنه كان شعورًا جميلًا يحدث لي لأول مرة.
How is that possible?
كيف يكون ذلك ممكننًا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
MZ: So creativity, I learned, means different things to different people.
(مانوش): عرفت أن للإبداع معان أخرى
But everyone found day three's challenge the hardest.
إلا أن تحدي اليوم الثالث كان الأصعب لكل المشاركين
It was called "Delete that app."
كان يُسمّى "احذف التطبيق"
Take that app -- you know the one;
ذلك التطبيق .. نعم أنتم تعرفونه
that one that always gets you, it sucks you in --
الذي يأخذ وقتك دائمًا،
take it off your phone,
احذفه من جهازك
even if just for the day.
حتى لو في هذا اليوم فقط.
I deleted the game Two Dots and nearly cried.
مسحت لعبة Two Dots و أنا أبكي تقريبًا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, Two Dots players know what I'm talking about.
الذين يلعبون بها سيعرفون شعوري
But my misery had good company.
لكن هناك من شاركني حزني.
(Audio) Man 2: This is Liam in Los Angeles,
(صوت): أنا ليام من لوس أنجلوس
and I deleted Twitter, Facebook, Instagram, Tumblr, Snapchat and Vine
حذفت تويتر وفيسبوك وانستجرام وتمبلر وسناب شات وفاين
from my phone
من هاتفي
in one fell swoop.
مرة واحدة.
And it was kind of an embarrassingly emotional experience at first.
كانت تجربة صعبة في البداية
It felt weirdly lonely to look at that lock screen
وشعرت بوحدة غريبة وأنا انظر إلى الشاشة المقفلة
with no new notifications on it.
بدون ظهور أي تنبيهات عليها.
But I really liked deciding for myself
لكنني أحببت أن يكون القرار ملكي
when to think about or access my social networks,
لأفكر أو أتصفّح وسائل التواصل تلك،
not giving my phone the power to decide that for me.
ولا أعطي الفرصة لجهازي ليتخذ هذا القرار بدلًا مني.
So thank you.
أشكركم على هذه التجربة.
(Audio) Woman 3: Deleting the Twitter app was very sad,
(صوت امرأة): حذف تطبيق تويتر كان أمرًا حزينًا للغاية
and I feel I maybe, over the last year when I've been on Twitter,
وشعرت أني قد أكون وقعت في إدمان تويتر
have developed an addiction to it,
خلال تواجدي فيه السنة الماضية
and this "Bored and Brilliant" challenge has really made me realize it.
وهذا التحدي (ضجر ومميز) جعلني أفهم ذلك واستوعبه
After a brief period of really horrible withdrawal feeling,
وبعد فترة وجيزة من شعور الانسحاب الرهيب حقا،
like lack-of-caffeine headache,
كأنه صداع بسبب قلة الكافيين،
I now feel lovely.
فأنا أشعر بالطمأنينة الآن،
I had a lovely dinner with my family,
وأقضي وقتًا جميلًا بالعشاء مع عائلتي،
and I hope to continue this structured use of these powerful tools.
وأتمنى أن يستمر هذا الاستخدام المنظم لهذه الأدوات القوية.
(Audio) Woman 4: I don't have that guilty gut feeling
(صوت امرأة): لا أشعر بالذنب
I have when I know I'm wasting time on my phone.
مثلما أشعر به وأنا أضيع وقتي على الهاتف
Maybe I'll have to start giving myself challenges and reminders like this
ربما أنا بحاجة لأعطاء نفسي بعض التحديات وأذكرها بمثل هذا
every morning.
كل صباح.
MZ: I mean, yes, this was progress.
(مانوش): نعم كان هذا تقدمًا.
I could not wait to see what the numbers said
لم أستطع الانتظار لمعرفة ما تقوله الأرقام
at the end of that week.
في نهاية ذلك الاسبوع.
But when the data came in,
لكن حينما جاءت
it turned out that we had cut down,
أظهرت أن هناك انخفاض في
on average,
معدلات الاستخدام
just six minutes --
فقط لست دقائق ..
from 120 minutes a day on our phones
من 120 دقيقة يوميًا
to 114.
إلى 114.
Yeah. Whoop-de-do.
لا فائدة.
So I went back to the scientists feeling kind of low,
عدت مجددًا إلى المختصين وأنا محبطة
and they just laughed at me,
لكنهم ضحكوا علي
and they said, you know, changing people's behavior
وقالوا أن تغيير سلوك الناس
in such a short time period
في مثل هذه الفترة القصيرة
was ridiculously ambitious,
طموح مثير للضحك
and actually what you've achieved is far beyond what we thought possible.
والحقيقة أن ما تحقق بعيد عمّا كنا نظنه ممكنًا
Because more important than the numbers, were the people's stories.
لأن ما تحدث به الناس أكثر أهمية مما تظهره الأرقام
They felt empowered.
لقد شعروا أنهم أقوياء متمكنين.
Their phones had been transformed
وتحوّلت هواتفهم
from taskmasters
من إدارة للمهام
back into tools.
إلى مجرد أدوات لتنفيذها.
And actually, I found what the young people said most intriguing.
والحقيقة أني وجدت ما قاله الصغار مثيرًا للاهتمام.
Some of them told me
فقد قال لي بعضهم
that they didn't recognize some of the emotions
أنهم لم يدركوا بعض المشاعر
that they felt during challenge week,
التي أحسّوا بها خلال اسبوع التحدي.
because, if you think about it,
لأنه إذا فكرت في هذا،
if you have never known life without connectivity,
إذا لم تجرّب الحياة أبدًا بدون انترنت
you may never have experienced boredom.
فأنت لن تجرب الشعور بالملل مطلقًا.
And there could be consequences.
وقد يكون هناك توابع لهذا الأمر.
Researchers at USC have found -- they're studying teenagers
باحثون في جامعة كاليفورنيا الجنوبية وجدوا وهم يدرسون المراهقين
who are on social media while they're talking to their friends
المستخدمين لوسائل التواصل الاجتماعي خلال أحاديثهم مع أصدقائهم
or they're doing homework,
أو أداء واجباتهم المنزلية
and two years down the road, they are less creative and imaginative
لمدة سنتين، أنهم أقل ابداعًا وخيالًا
about their own personal futures
حول مستقبلهم الشخصي
and about solving societal problems, like violence in their neighborhoods.
وحول قدرتهم على حل المشاكل الإجتماعية، مثل العنف في مناطقهم.
And we really need this next generation
نحن بحاجة حقيقية أن يكون الجيل القادم
to be able to focus on some big problems:
قادر على التركيز على بعض الأمور الكبيرة:
climate change, economic disparity,
تغير المناخ، والتفاوت الاقتصادي،
massive cultural differences.
الاختلافات الثقافية الهائلة.
No wonder CEOs in an IBM survey
لا غرابة أن مديري IBM التنفيذين
identified creativity as the number one leadership competency.
وضعوا الابتكار كأول كفاءة مطلوبة للقيادة.
OK, here's the good news, though:
حسنٌ، هنا النتائج الجيدة رغم ذلك،
In the end, 20,000 people did "Bored and Brilliant" that week.
في النهاية فإن 20,000 شخص شاركوا في تحدي "ضجر ومميز".
Ninety percent cut down on their minutes.
90% منهم انخفضت معدلات استخدامهم.
Seventy percent got more time to think.
70% أصبح لديهم وقت أكثر للتفكّر والتأمّل.
People told me that they slept better.
قالوا لي أن نومهم أصبح أفضل،
They felt happier.
وكانوا أكثر سعادة.
My favorite note was from a guy who said he felt like he was waking up
أفضل ملاحظة كانت من شاب قال أنه شعر وكأنه استيقظ
from a mental hibernation.
من سبات عقلي.
Some personal data and some neuroscience
إذن فقد استفدنا من المعلومات الشخصية ومن علم الأعصاب
gave us permission to be offline a little bit more,
سمحت لنا بأن نكون غير متصلين بعض الوقت
and a little bit of boredom gave us some clarity
وقليلأ من الملل أعطانا بعض الصفاء
and helped some of us set some goals.
وساعد البعض في وضع بعض الأهداف.
I mean, maybe constant connectivity
ربما يكون الاتصال المستمر
won't be cool in a couple of years.
أمر غير محبب في السنوات القادمة
But meanwhile, teaching people, especially kids,
ولكن في الوقت نفسه، فإن تعليم الناس وخاصة الأطفال
how to use technology to improve their lives
كيفية استخدام التقنية ليحسّنوا من حياتهم
and to self-regulate
وينظّموا أنفسهم
needs to be part of digital literacy.
لا بد أن يكون من أبجديات التقنية
So the next time you go to check your phone,
إذن المرة القادمة التي ستتصفح فيها هاتفك
remember that if you don't decide how you're going to use the technology,
تذكر أنك إذا لم تقرر كيف ستستخدم هذه التقنية
the platforms will decide for you.
سوف تقرر هي بدلًا عنك.
And ask yourself:
واسأل نفسك:
What am I really looking for?
ما الذي أريده منها؟
Because if it's to check email, that's fine -- do it and be done.
لأنه إذا كنت تريد أن تتصفح إيميلك، فلا بأس، تصفحه وانتهى من الأمر.
But if it's to distract yourself from doing the hard work
أما إذا إذا تريد تُلهي نفسك عن إنجاز أعمالك
that comes with deeper thinking,
ففكّر في ذلك مليًّا،
take a break,
خذ قسطًا من الراحة،
stare out the window
وافتح النافذة
and know that by doing nothing
واعلم أن عدم فعلك لأي شيء
you are actually being your most productive and creative self.
أنك في الحقيقة تكون أكثر ابداعًا وابتكارًا
It might feel weird and uncomfortable at first,
ربما تشعر بالقلق وعدم الراحة في البداية،
but boredom truly can lead to brilliance.
لكن الملل بإمكانه أن يقودك إلى التألق والابداع.
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)